<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>St. foine improved a discourse shewing the utility and benefit which England hath and may receive by the grasse called St. Foine and answering the objections urged against it ... / written by a person of honour lately deceased.</title>
            <author>Person of honour lately deceased.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9267</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13539678</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13539678</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 472:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>St. foine improved a discourse shewing the utility and benefit which England hath and may receive by the grasse called St. Foine and answering the objections urged against it ... / written by a person of honour lately deceased.</title>
                  <author>Person of honour lately deceased.</author>
                  <author>Pettus, John, Sir, 1613-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. G. and B. G. for Nath. Brooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Incorrectly attributed to John Pettus.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sainfoin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100067:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100067:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> Foine Improved, A DISCOURSE Shewing the <hi>Vtility</hi> and
<hi>Benefit</hi> which ENGLAND Hath and may receive by the GRASSE CALLED S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> FOINE, And anſwering the Objections urged againſt it.</p>
            <p>Being uſeful for all Ingenious Men.</p>
            <p>Written by a Perſon of Honour lately deceaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> and <hi>E. G.</hi> for
<hi>Nath. Brooke,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1671.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="description" type="crop">
            <pb facs="tcp:100067:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100067:2"/>
            <head>St. Foine Improved, OR THE GRASSE CALLED St. FOINE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Vindicated and Commended to all that delight in Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, and other ingenious Men.</head>
            <p>NOtwithſtanding the great benefit which divers places of this Kingdome have already in part, and are like hereafter to receive more abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the improvement of dry and barren Ground, and the increaſe of Paſture and Meadow upon them, through the Sewing of the Graſs-ſeed called
<hi>St. Foine,</hi> yet there are not wanting ſome, who not only ſpeak themſelves, but would alſo engage the State againſt it; as if the common Mother of all the People, could be perſwaded to diſcourage the induſtry of ſome of her Children (for the common good and wealth of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as well as their own particular advantage) to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſome others with the monopoly of all the Hay and Herbage thereof; and to ſatisfie rather their imaginary fears (as anon ſhall be declared) than their real ſufferings; although all they can ſuffer, is but the abatement of that <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100067:3"/>gain which they have ſo long time made by the ſufferings of their Neighbours, making their advantages upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers neceſſities: And it were very great partiality, to force any part (and by far the greater part of the Nation to labour ſtill under their neceſſities, and not to ſuffer them to ſupply themſelves by the improvement of their own Grounds (which proportionably improveth the ſtock and riches of the Nation) that ſome Men might ſtill have the opportunity to ſell their Hay, and let their Paſture ſo much the dearer.</p>
            <p>If theſe Men could alleadge, that by this improvement of the dry and barten Ground, their rich Grounds were made poorer, or leſs fruitful, or that what was abated in their Lands was gained by Forraigners, and not by their own fellow Subjects (which ſecureth the Kingdome from any loſs) they had more colour of reaſon on their ſide; but in this caſe they have none at all: For as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth receives no detriment by it, ſo neither doth any particular man receive any prejudice thereby, but by accident, if at all; but on the other ſide the Kingdome in general is thereby enriched, many private men advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged in their eſtates, without the leaſt injury to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Man whatſoever: for it is well known how great and vaſt a quantity of Land there hath been, and ſtill is in <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Wales,</hi> which of its own nature is neither Meadow, or any confiderable paſturage, in reſpect of ſo great a proportion of ground, inſomuch that the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of divers places have been forced to buy Hay at ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive dear rates, 20 <abbr>s.</abbr> 30 <abbr>s.</abbr> 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> and ſometimes 3 <abbr>l.</abbr> and 5 <abbr>l.</abbr> a Tun, and to fetch it by Cart, ſix, ten, fifteen miles. Others have been forced to ſupply the want of Hay by Turnips (as in <hi>Norfolk</hi>) and all this not ſufficing, men have ſet their wits on work to get more Paſture and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100067:3"/>whereupon, great Levels of Fens have been Drain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſome Countries; and in other places Meadow and Paſture hath been exceedingly increaſed by the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of dry and courſe Grounds, and thoſe that having ſo done, have had opportunity to ſell their Hay, and ſet their Herbage at very dear rates to their neighbours, now that their own turn is ſerved, they would pull up the ladder (as they ſay) after them, and would hinder others from improving their dry Grounds, in ſuch ways as they are capable of improvement; as if the Rain were to fall, and the Sun to ſhine only on ſome Mens Lands. The Men of the Vale might as well deſire that thoſe of the Hill-country might not Fold, or Dung their Ground, or Sow any Corn, that ſo (having no Corn of their own) they might be forced to buy it at a higher rate from thoſe of the Dale; and with far greater ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of reaſon might they urge ſuch a reſtraint, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Vale being the Granary of the Kingdom would thereby be encouraged to Sow more Corn, and forbear to turn ſo much Tillage into Paſture, and that the Tillage of the Hill-countries doth but waſte the ſtrength of Men and Beaſts, and the ſtock of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to little purpoſe, and will fail the Nation in dry years, and ſupply it but a little in wet years. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Wood-land-countries might with as good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon deſire that no
<hi>French</hi> Furze might be ſown (as in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire</hi> and
<hi>Cornwall</hi>) nor any Wood planted in naked Countries, that they might ſell their Wood the dearer, or that no Turfs or Coals might be made uſe of, (as I have heard) that when Sea-coal began to be firſt burnt in
<hi>London,</hi> thoſe that feared the fall of their Wood from the prizes they formerly ſold at, procured a Petition to be preferred to the Houſe of Commons, againſt the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Sea-coal, as corrupting the Air of the City. Now <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100067:4"/>though there is hardly any thing ſo innocent, or uſeful to Mankind, but that envy, and ſelf-intereſt may find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in it to cavil at, yet could I never hitherto hear of any thing that was objected particularly againſt this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement by <hi>St. Foine,</hi> faving only that it fills the Nation with over much Meadow and Paſture, which if it be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted a nuiſance, the ſame thing bath been done many other ways, and thoſe not altogether free from particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar exceptions againſt them.</p>
            <p>It cannot be objected here, as againſt the Draining of the Fens, or the watering of Meadow, that the Slabb and Mud which remains after the Water is drawn off the Ground, and the Suns heat comes upon, it corrupts the Air, and makes it unwholeſome. Nor that it indanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Cattle with the Murrain, for want of Water, in dry years, as it is found that low and Fen-grounds do, or that it rotteth or deceiveth Gattle (as the Hay of ſome watred Ground doth) and which is but courſe, and not very good for Sheep at the beſt. Nor that it deſtroys any Fiſh, or prejudices any Mill, nor hinders Navigation, or pens the Water up too long upon other Mens Ground above, or keeps it too long from them below, or that thereby any mans ground is cut away, or that any Mans Common, Fiſhing, Fowling, or other way of live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood is deſtroyed, or that the Water is carried off one part, to lye heavier, and more dangerouſly on another ſide. All, or ſome of which, may be truly objected againſt Draining of Fens, and Watering of Meadows, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all which the Kingdome hath been thought in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſo much advantaged by the increaſe of Paſture and Meadow (all which <hi>St, Foine</hi> doth, as anon ſhall be ſhewn) that it hath by particular Acts countenanced the own, and never diſcountenanced the other.</p>
            <p>But now ſay ſome (and this is the only objection that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100067:4"/>ever I heard againſt <hi>St. Foine</hi>) there is ſo much Meadow and Paſture in the Kingdome, that there is not ſtock to ſpend it. A ſtrange paradox, that plenty ſhould make the Kingdome poor; but before I ſpeak directly to that principle (which is that of all monopoliſts, tending to the inriching of a few, by the impoveriſhing of many) I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand how doth the truth of this aſſertion appear; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in ſome parts, where in plentiful years there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Hay to ſpare, eſpecially where they were uſed to ſell their Hay, and never look out to provide ſtock, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they conclude, that it is ſo generally and conſtantly; whereas there cannot be a clearer demonſtration of the contrary, than the coſt Men are ſtill at of 40 <abbr>s.</abbr> and 50 <abbr>s.</abbr> an Acre to improve their Grounds by <hi>St. Foine,</hi> which they would never do if they knew not how to get ſtock to eat their Graſs and Hay, when they had been at ſo much coſt, aad charge to promote it. Nay, it is ſo far from that, that notwithſtanding the great plenty of old Hay, that was left the laſt year, and the improvement by <hi>St. Foine,</hi> the Inhabitants (even in ſome Pariſhes where there is a conſiderable proportion of <hi>St. Foine</hi>) have yet this laſt year bought Hay at 20 <abbr>s.</abbr> the Tun and more, and fetched it ſix miles and more by Cart. And I know a Gentleman that hath above 40. Acres of <hi>St. Foine,</hi> and yet is forced ſtill to buy Hay for the ordinary ſtock of his Farm: And ſurely none need to fear, but if there be Meat there will be Mouths, and the increaſe of Graſs and Hay will proportionably increaſe the ſtock of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and as there is more ſuſtinance for Cattle, there will be more buyers of them, and then there will be more Breeders; and rather than ſtock ſhould be wanting, the Improvers by <hi>St. Foine</hi> will in time breed for themſelves and others too, that Graſs having a ſpecial quality to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <pb n="6" facs="tcp:100067:5"/>ſtore of Milk, and that very good, whence amongſt other names it is called <hi>Idygala,</hi> and will be as proper to breed, as to feed Cattel.</p>
            <p>Now whereas ſome are ready to impute the abatement of the price of their rich Grounds and Meadow, to the improvement of <hi>St. Foine,</hi> it is in (probability) but a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of <hi>non cauſa pro cauſa,</hi> for there hath not been ſo much of it yet ſown, as that it can be generally felt through the Kingdome, as the abatement of Rents hath been, and that as much or more in ſuch Countries where none of that Graſs hath been, nor in many miles near them, as in thoſe Countries where it hath been Sown. And as much or more in Farms chiefly conſiſting of Corn, and little of Meadow and Paſture, and that for theſe ten years laſt paſt, when very little
<hi>St. Foine</hi> was Sown or ſpoken off. So that ſuch abatements of Rent muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſome other cauſes of the general decay in Trade.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, that which is feared will be an effect of this, and the like improvements, is not like to be, for the Sowing of <hi>St. Foine</hi> doth not make the rich Grounds, and Meadows poor, or more barren. And whereas it may be thought that the more plenty there is of Graſs and Hay, of the leſs value they will be, that doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low neither, and if it did, yet would there no inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereby happen to the publick. I ſay it doth not neceſſarily follow, that the more ſtore there ſhould be of Hay and Graſs, the cheaper they ſhould be, for as I ſaid before, the more meat the more mouths both of Men and Beaſts, and the more of them the more Merchandizers, the more Manufactures, and the more Money; and every way the more will be the Riches, Strength, Proſperity, and Glory of a Nation. It may be, that as an uncertain <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100067:5"/>temper of weather (ſometimes heats and ſometimes colds) is prejudicial to the natural body, ſo will an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and vatiable ſtate of ſcarcity and plenty prove hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the body politick, the one ſtarving, and the other glutting it; but whatſoever layeth a foundation of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain plenty, muſt needs be of great advantage to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; and though there may be ſome little appearing, or poſſibily ſome real loſs to ſome Men, till ſuch time as they have accommodated their particular concerns and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, to ſuch alteration in Trade, as may happen upon a new Improvement, and till ſuch time as plenty hath wrought out it ſelf a vent, yet this loſs is no other than ſuch as the Husbandman ſeems to ſuſtain in caſting away his Seed, which he will find again at Harveſt with great advantage. As for example, in this Improvement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſuſtenance of all ſorts of Cattle is increaſed, as Men find they have more keeping, ſo will they look out for more ſtock of all ſorts, and the more Buyers there be the more Breeders there will alſo be, and the more Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers the more Feeders, the means of feeding as well as of breeding being increaſed. So that ſcarcity of Hay and Graſs will ſooner make goods cheap than plenty thereof, for Men will not buy above the prop rtion of the means they have to maintain or feed of what they buy, and yet thoſe that are neceſſitated to ſell for want of means to keep their ſtock muſt ſell though at low rates, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is when there are but few that have means to keep ſtock, is the advantage of thoſe few, becauſe they may buy cheap, and ſell deat, but withal it is (as all Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies are) very diſadvantagious to the publick; for it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages the Breeders of Stock, and the leſs Stock the leſs Compoſt and Dung, and the fewer working Oxen and Horſes, and ſo the leſs Corn, and the leſs Meat, Drink,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100067:6"/>and Cloathing, the fewer people will be in a Nation, and ſo fewer Souldiers, fewer Tradeſmen, fewer Merchants, becauſe fewer Workmen, and fewer Materials to work upon, and leſſer ſuſtinance for the Workmen.</p>
            <p>And if it ſhall be demanded where we ſhall have a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ſtock of Men? I anſwer, there is little doubt of the fertility of theſe Northern Nations of <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Scotland,</hi> if the want of means and ſubſiſtance did not put a reſtraint upon Marriage (which draws after it divers other inconveniences, of Baſtards, Beggars, <hi>&amp;c</hi> and we find by experience that the richeſt Countries are beſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled, and freeſt from Beggars; and it is not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that as the good husbandry of Denſuring or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhering of Land (and the like) hath rendred the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of
<hi>Devonſhire</hi> a rich and populous Country, which of its own nature is but a barren Soill. So in time will this improvement by <hi>St. Foine,</hi> and other ſuch like, render the Downy and dry parts of <hi>England</hi> and
<hi>Wales</hi> more rich and populous. And if it might be ſuppoſed that the Kings Dominions could not afford a ſufficient ſtock of Men and Cattle, for the conſumption and working of inner Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities when increaſed: Plenty of good and valuable Commodities will draw Men from all parts of the world, or at leaſt ſuch Commodities will be of value in all parts of the world.</p>
            <p>If we had ſuch plenty of Corn, Meat, Tallow, Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Butter, Cheeſe, Wax, and Honey, (for them alſo <hi>St. Foine</hi> will certainly increaſe Bees, ſo exceedingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting to feed on the Flowers thereof) as that with the ſurpluſage of our own Conſumption we might ſend over great quantities beyond Seas, and alſo be able out of our own aboundance to under ſell other Nations, we ſhould not need to fear the vent of them, for our Commodities <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100067:6"/>would be moſt vendible, becauſe cheapeſt. Beſides, by having a great quantity of ſuch ſubſtantial Commodities for the life of Man to Tranſport, we ſhould bring our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to be far greater than our Import, which now is fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to fall be ow it, and to be the chief cauſe of the want of Money, and Conſequently of the decay of Trade in the Kingdome, and muſt needs (if not prevented) in time begger it in the end.</p>
            <p>But to ſuch as are afraid of plenty, I ſhall further ſay, that it is greater riches not to need, than to have much money. What are Men the worſe, though they receive leſs money from their Lands or goods, if all things they ſtand in need of for Meat, Drink, Cloathing, and other neceſſaries, may be bought with leſs money. And what if Men ſell off Goods cheaper, if they can buy them in as much cheaper.</p>
            <p>Indeed ſome perſons would not have ſo much Money in their Pockets to carry on a Trade, which is neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitable to themſelves, nor the Kingdome, but very preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to both; that is exceſſive Gameing, and Betting at Cockings, and Races, and other ſuperfluous, that I may not ſay, luxurious expences upon Forraign Commodities, tending (for the moſt part) to the impairing of the health of the body, or to the nouriſhing and venting of the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the mind, and withal exhauſting the eſtates of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Men, and the general ſtock of the Kingdome, or at leaſt diverting ſo much thereof from uſeful Trades and Imployments, to thoſe that are far from being uſeful or profitable. Wherein if Gentlemen would by their own moderation ſet a law to themſelves, or that there might be a reſtraint put upon them by wholeſome Laws (as the <hi>Romans</hi> both anciently, and of latter times under the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ours were very ſtrict therein) there would not be ſuch <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100067:7"/>great ſums of money diverted from the Trade of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the carrying on of ſuch ſuperfluous and vain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences (I ſpeak as to the exceſs) whilſt others in the mean time keep up their monies, for to be ready to purchaſe the Eſtates of ſuch Unthriſts at eaſie rates, to omit many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inconveniences that follow thereupon: If ſuch as have no Lands left to be improved by <hi>St. Foine</hi> (as few that have any conſiderable eſtates but have) would ſpare ſomewhat out of ſuch ſuperfluous and hurtful ways of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, they may at eaſie rates enough purchaſe good quantities of ſuch Lands, which by this way of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement they might ſufficiently ballance any dammage they doubt they might ſuſtain thereby in their rich Grounds and Meadows.</p>
            <p>Again, as I ſaid before, that he is richer that needs not money, than he that hath it, ſo the beſt way for a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to have plenty of money is not to need it; for it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that drains away the money of a Nation, and forc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to buy of Forraigners at dear rates, but when they have abundance for all neceſſary uſes of their own, what they have to ſpare brings them in ſo much clear money without any deductions for the ſupply of their own wants from abroad; and the cheaper our Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities are in Forraign Markers, the more money will come into the Nation in the end, and make our Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities the moſt vendible, becauſe cheapeſt, and becauſe we are able to afford them ſo. And the contrary courſe held by our Merchant-Adventurers in ſtarving the Markets beyond Sea hath not a little prejudiced us in our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture of Cloath, inforcing other Nations out of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſet up the Manufacture of Cloath, which they neither would, nor could have done (having none or few Materials of their own growth) if we had not held our Cloath at <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100067:7"/>too high rates, and ſerved Forraign Markets ſo ſparingly, ſo that our Neighbours are now able in ſome ſort of Cloaths to under ſell us. I have ſaid all this to ſatisfie the doubts and jealouſies of ſuch as are the owners of rich Paſtures and Meadows: but now admitting they may have ſome cauſe of jealouſie and doubt; yea, ſay it be ſome dammage for a while, yet if it ſhall excite their indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, as neceſſity hath done theirs that were poſſeſſors of dry and barren Lands, <hi>Faelix neceſſitas quae ad meliora con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducit,</hi> and thoſe that have rich Grounds, have far the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ground to work upon, for rich Soils are capable of holding their value at leaſt, if not of improvement ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways; but the dry and high Grounds are capable of very few ways of improvement. If increaſe of Paſture and Meadow in the hill and barren Countries, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce men in the vale and other parts to return again to Tillage, and eſpecially to imploy ſome of their rich Grounds for Hemp and Flax, though it might be ſome trouble and coſt at the firſt, it would after turn to far greater profit to the owners, and of ſingular advantage to the publick, by the increaſe of ſuch fort of Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of our own growth, and the Manufactures relate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto, beſides the advantage which would after acrew by the change of the Seed; ſometimes one ſort of Grain, and ſometimes another, which thoſe Grounds would bring forth in great abundance; as alſo Rape and Cole-ſeed, all ſorts of Fruits and Garden-ſtuff, and after return to good Paſture and Meadow again. A rich Soil is capable of any thing almoſt, and the conſtantly uſing of it one way, only gratifieth ſloath and idleneſs; but ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable change of the beſt ſuits with the nature of almoſt all Grounds, but eſpecially of rich Soils, and is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitable to the owners, and to the publick.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:100067:8"/>
            <p>I ſhall now add ſomething, as to the parallel which I heat ſome in diſcourſe make between <hi>St. Foine</hi> and the Planting Tabacco in <hi>England,</hi> as if there were the like reaſon for the prohibiting of the one, as of the other; whereas the difference between them is very appatent in Reaſon; Juſtice, and Policy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> in Reaſon, for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tabacco (which is laid down as a principal reaſon for the reſtraint thereof) is not ſo whole ſome as that which comes from beyond Sea, nor in reaſon can be, for want of the like influence of the Sun; whereas <hi>St. Foine</hi> is ſo far from being unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, that it is the moſt wholeſome Graſs that Cattle can eat; from whence ſome have thought it to be called <hi>St. Foine,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>ſanum, faenum,</hi> but 'tis indeed called in <hi>French St. Foine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Country-farm <hi>page</hi> 697 and 698.</note> that is <hi>ſanctum faenum;</hi> for that as ſome ſay (and thoſe Doctors of Phyſick too) it may ſeem ſeem to ſpring out of the Earth, as it were of a more eſpecial favour from God, not only for the nouriſhing and facting of Herds of Cattle, but alſo to ſerve for Phyſick for Beaſts that are ſick, and in that reſpect is called of the Latines <hi>Medica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> there was cauſe to reſtrain the Planting of
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Tabacco in Juſtice to thoſe that have adventured their lives and fortunes in thoſe Colonies; ſo far off from their Native Countries, for the in largentent of the Kings Territories and Dominions, and have engaged themſelves to vend their Tabacco, only in his Majeſties Dominions, upon promiſe and aſſurance, that their Trade ſhould not be prejudiced by the Planting of Tabacco here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the owners of rich Ground and Meadows have no ſuch point of Juſtice to inſiſt upon in oppoſition to ſuch as improve their Lands by <hi>St. Foine,</hi> but on the <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100067:8"/>other ſide it would be great partlality, if not in juſtice, to hinder men from improving their Land by their induſtry, which of common right every man may do and will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged therein by every wiſe State, if the publick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no prejudice there by, as in this improvement I doth not but great advantage; neither doth any particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lar man ſuffer any injury thereby; for if he did, the Law would do him right, nor can any man ſuffer thereby, but by accident, (if at all) nor at all, but out of his ſloth and want of induſtry.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In Policy: As the Caſes relate to the Publick, there is a vaſt and wide difference. For in that of Engliſh Tabacco, as is largely declared in the preamble of the Act, the Navigation of the Kingdom, and the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof, the inlargement of the King's Domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons and Territories by thoſe American Colonies, the vent of our native Commodities to them, the great Trade that relates to them, and the King's Cuſtoms out of it would be loſt, or much impaired, only to gratifie a few Perſors in a pedling profit, which they attempt to make in ſome patches of Ground, to raiſe a ſmall quantity of unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Tabacco, which could not (in any ſort) ſupply the defect of the other; much leſs countervail all thoſe other great and weighty Conſiderations before mentioned, and yet might be ſufficient to diſcourage thoſe Plantations, which after would not be ſo eaſily reſtored again.</p>
            <p>But in the improvement by St. Foine there is nothing of all this, or like it, but the contrary in all reſpects. It is ſo far from prejudicing Navigation, or any of the Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Colonies, that it rather promoteth both, by furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Kingdom with great aboundance of ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities as we vent there, and in other parts, whereby more Shipping will be imployed, and alſo by this meant <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100067:9"/>there will be a greater plenty of Beef, Butter-Cheeſe, &amp;c. for the Proviſion of Ships and Seamen: Neither is there any danger of deſtroying a great and certain Trade, in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to raiſe a petty one, that will in no ſort ſupply the want, or countervail the damage of the other. For ſhould St. Foine fail (as Clover Graſs doth in a few years) the rich Grounds, and watted Meadows, are not thereby made more barren, or leſs capable to ſupply the neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Nation then they were before; neither are the Grounds ſowed with St. Foine made barren thereby after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, but on the contrary, it renders Ground more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and fit for Corn; in ſo much that ſuch Ground as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was would bring none, or very mean crops of Corn, being ploughed up after St. Foine, the roots thereof are as good as any dung unto it, and will make it bear ſome good crops of Corn; and then being ſowed again with St. Foine, it will, bear it again as well as ever it did; ſo that it may continually be renewed when the ſpirit of it is ſpent, with the advantage of ſome intervening crops of Corn: And in this ſort they in other Countries do or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it; and ſo no doubt ſhall we alſo do in England, when there is more plenty of it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, there is not any ſort of improvement more profitable, and withal ſo innocent as this; for moſt of other improvements, together with their uſefulneſs, are ſome ways injurions to particular men, and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to the Publick (as in watred Meadows, and draining of Fens hath before been remembred) and yet there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing objected againſt St. Foine, which might not and may not equally be objected againſt them, if the increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Meadow and Paſture be a nuiſance. And they that are equally and firſt in the tranſgreſſion, ought equally and firſt to be ſuppreſt: and much rather then an improvement <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100067:9"/>whereof the uſefulneſs is very great, and in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars (as anon ſhall be remarked) not to be paralelled by any ſort of Natural or Artificial Herbage or Fodder what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and yet it is ſo far from being injurious to any, that it doth not ſo much as offend the ſenſes, by any ill ſight or ſmell, as watering and burning Ground doth, but is very, pleaſant to the eye by its Vernal and Autumnal verdure and Summers purple veſture, which Flowers (from whence the Bees ſo greedily ſuck their Nectar) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but render the Air alſo more ſweet and wholeſome.</p>
            <p>To ſum up in the end of my diſcourſe the Commodities which will accrew to particular Men, and the Publick by St. Foine; I ſhall mention in the firſt place that which the oppoſers of it (out of a principle common to all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoliſts) call a nuiſance, <hi>viz.</hi> the increaſe and plenty of Paſture and Meadow, and conſequently of the ſtock of ſtore, and wealth of the Kingdom; and that eſpecially in ſuch places where there was, and yet is moſt need thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Graſs and Hay that is raiſed thereby, is beyond all ſorts of Graſs and Fodder, in that it is not only Meat, but Medicine, as hath before been ſaid.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this Graſs when once well rooted, runneth down ſo deep into the Ground, that is neither in danger of heat not cold, ſtirreth betimes in the Spring, laſteth long in the Autumn, ſpringeth ſuddenly again after it is cut down or fed, and wherein it exceedeth all ſorts of Paſture and Meadow, (except ſome watered Meadows on great Rivers, which is not without ſome prejudice to Mills and Navigation.) In the drieſt years, when all the richeſt Paſture and up-land Meadows are burnt away, this will be both good Paſture and Meadow. What a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief then would it be to deprive the Kingdom of ſuch a <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100067:10"/>Commedity, which will ſupply its neceſſities, when other means generally fail.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, this Graſs is good both for breeding and feeding of all ſorts of Cattle, and begetteth ſo much Milk, and ſo good, that the Dary maid ſhall in one weeks ſpace find a great alteration for the better, both in the colour, quantity, and quality of the Milk, from what any ordinary Paſture will yield.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, (to conclude with that ſweet and very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Commodity It muſt certainly raiſe very much and very good Honey and Wax, Bees delighting ſo much to feed upon it.</p>
            <p>And therefore unleſs that which God promiſed as a Bleſsing to the Iſraelites, ſeem a Curſe to <hi>England, viz.</hi> A Land flowing with Milk and Honey. I hope no man will from henceforth indeavor to hinder the increaſe of St. Foine.</p>
            <p>This and the like improvements (if incouraged) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but make the Nation rich, populous and proſperous as we ſee that of our Neighbors of
<hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanaers</hi> are, from whenee we learn theſe and the like improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but if we ſhall chuſe to follow them in their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Superfluities, and ſhall not withal imitate them in their Vertues and Induſtry, but diſcourage what they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and thrive ſo much by; we may juſtly fear, we ſhall be the Tail and not the Head; always Borrowers and Buyers, and never Lenders or Venders: and ſo become the Object of all our Neighbors Affronts and Scorns, which God forbid.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="husbandry" type="crop">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100067:10"/>
            <head>THE SOILS, HVSBANDRY, And VSES proper for S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> FOINE VVith the ſeveral Manners of its Improvement; Fit to be known by all that delight in
<hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDRY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Soils proper for <hi>St. Foine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſoils proper.</note> are the moſt of dry Grounds, though they be very bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, trial having been made plentifully on Stony and Chalky Grounds, not worth two ſhillings the Acre, which have thereby been improved to be worth forty ſhillings the Acre, and have ſo continued for thirty years.</p>
            <p>Sheer and ſleight Sands,<note place="margin">The impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſoils.</note> are the only proper dry Grounds; but mixed Sands, as are generally the Red and Brown, bear it ſingularly well: all Clays and other cold and wet Grounds bear it not.</p>
            <p>The times of ſowing it are in <hi>Autumn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The times of ſowing.</note> from the beginning of
<hi>August,</hi> till the end of <hi>September:</hi> In the <hi>Spring,</hi> from the beginning of <hi>February</hi> till the end of <hi>March;</hi> but the earlier it is ſown in either ſeaſon the better.</p>
            <p>For ſowing it in <hi>Autumn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sowing it in
<hi>Autumn.</hi>
               </note> the Tillage ought to in all reſpects the ſame as for Wheat, with this difference: That before it be ſown, the land muſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100067:11"/>be harrowed very fine to level it: Then ſew it, and harrow it in, as other Grains.</p>
            <p>There is this way alſo of doing it with ſmall charge,<note place="margin">Another way.</note> and good ſucceſs. If Land be ſowed with Summer-Corn, and is very free from Weeds, let the Corn be Mowed low; and ſo ſoon as it is off the Ground, turn up the Land with a Plow, and Harrow it very well, dragging off as much of the Stubble as conveniently may be; when it is fine, Sow the <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Foine,</hi> Harrowing it in, as before. To wrap or wreath, or raddle the ſpiks or teeth of the Harrow not to go into the Ground above two inches and an half.</p>
            <p>Note,<note place="margin">Note.</note> In the <hi>Autumn,</hi> it muſt ever be ſowed alone without Corn.</p>
            <p>In Spring,<note place="margin">Sowing in the Spring.</note> the Husbandry, it muſt be in all reſpects the ſame as for Batley: for the Land muſt be made very fine, and be Harrowed before it be ſowed, as is before directed. In this ſeaſon it may be ſown with Oats or Barley (but Oats are the better;) or without either, which is ſurely beſt.</p>
            <p>If without Corn,<note place="margin">Without Corn.</note> the manner of Husbandry differs not from the former Deſcription of ſowing it in the
<hi>Autumn.</hi> If with Corn, the Corn muſt be firſt ſowed and harrowed after the uſual manner; then ſow the <hi>St. Foine</hi> and harrow it, as before directed.</p>
            <p>New broken Ground cannot be ſowed with it,<note place="margin">With Corn new ground</note> till the Crop be firſt had; after which, the Ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſently turned up, and harrowed about
<hi>Alhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lontide,</hi> it will be fit to ſow the <hi>Spring</hi> following.</p>
            <p>To make preſent trial whether any Ground will bear it,<note place="margin">Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſent T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ial.</note> let a ſmall Plot about four yards ſquare be <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100067:11"/>digged with a Spade, and made fine with a Garden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and ſow the <hi>St. Foine</hi> in rows, as is wont to be done with Garden Peaſe: If the ground be ſward ground, the Turf muſt be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aven off and caſt away, that the remaining Earth may be fine: This muſt be carefully incloſed, and if it proſper well, it ſhews the ſoil proper: This may be done in ſeveral places, if the ſoil very, for more aſſurance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat on of it.</note>It muſt be carefully fenced and conſerved from Cattel the firſt year, nothing being ſuffered to come into it: the ſecond year generally it may be Mown, and the after-graſs fed about <hi>Alhollontide;</hi> but Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel would not be ſuffered to ſtay in it in wet ſeaſons till the root be ſtrong, which will be the third Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. If it be not of ſufficient growth to mow the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond year, (as in very dry Grounds, in cold and dry <hi>Springs</hi> it will not) it may then be fed with Cattel about the middle of <hi>May;</hi> but the Cattel would not be ſuffered to ſtay very long on it, for much treading will be hurtful to it being yet tender.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Uſes.</note>After the ſecond year, all the time it laſts, which is various (for in ſome ſoils it hath endured much longer then in others) it may be annually mowed or fed as is deſired, without any repair by dung, or other ſoile whatſoever: but it is not convenient to mow the ſame Grounds conſtantly, but they ſhould be ſometimes mowed, and other times fed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">For Hay.</note>If it muſt be reſerved for mowing, it muſt be laid in by the middle of <hi>April</hi> at lateſt, but
<hi>Lady day</hi> is a fitter time. It is fit to cut when it begins to flower, which commonly is about the middle of <hi>May,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times later: It is made in all reſpect as other Hay. <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100067:12"/>This Hay is very good for moſt uſes, that other Hay is; only it ſeems too groſs for Sheep, for Horſes it excels.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſeeding it g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een, with great beaſts.</note>When it is deſigned for Paſturage, it muſt be laid early, as the beginning of
<hi>March,</hi> which will render it fit to be fed by the middle of
<hi>April</hi> or <hi>May-day</hi> at lateſt. None but great Cattel would be paſtured on it at this time of the year, which it feeds ſingularly well, without danger of ſuffocation, which is inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to Clover-graſs. It breeds aboundance of Milk in Milch-Beaſts, and the Butter that is made of it is excellent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Feeding it with Sheep.</note>The After-Moth, and Graſs that ſprings in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn,</hi> in the Grounds that have been paſtured, may Sheep ſafely be fed with, which it fats ſuddenly: it is very good for Ews and Lambs, keeping them in high ſtate, and promoting growth, but they muſt not be ſuffered to go on it paſt
<hi>Lady-day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note there muſt be ſowed four Buſhels upon an Acre.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
